Jinjin Zhao

☑ j2zhao@uchicago.edu

**** +1 312 358 4946

jinjinz.com

? j2zhao

Interests _

I am interested in systems for data governance, particularly for data science and machine learning. In my research, I have worked on problems in Jupyter Notebook tracking, data lineage and provenance, and machine learning error classification. Currently, I am excited about applying database principles to semi-structured data management and building data systems that enhance model development.

Education _

PhD University of Chicago, Computer Science

Sept. 2019 to present

- Advisor: Sanjay Krishnan (ChiData Database Group)
- Completed M.S. degree as a part of Ph.D. program

BSE Princeton University, Computer Science

Sept. 2015 to May 2019

- · Graduated Summa Cum Laude
- · Minor in Statistics and Machine Learning

Projects _____

Understanding Datasets for Model Traning in Open Repositories (on-going)

- Exploring quantifiable factors to capture patterns in how datasets in open data repositories, like HuggingFace, are used
- · Creating a system that links results from secondary artifacts, such as research papers, to initial datasets

Tracing Variation in Data Science Workflows with Jupyter Notebook Logging

- Developed a custom tool for Jupyter Notebooks and Python to log execution traces of 93 data science assignments at the University of Chicago
- Analysed the traces to capture user variation trends in data science usage (e.g., most errors are resolved within 1-2 code executions)
- Validated some common conceptions in data science (e.g., data cleaning takes about 80% of the work)

A Compressed Query and Storage Framework for Fine-Grained Array Lineage

- Fine-grained array lineage is defined as tracking contributions from initial array cells to final array cells after some transformations
- Introduced new compression and query algorithms that improve storage space and query time by up to 2000x and 1500x, respectively.

Improving Triplet Labeling for Image Error Classification with Low-Dimension Features (on-going)

- Appling triplet labeling (i.e., given three images, chose the odd-one-out) to the problem of classifying machine learning errors in images
- Combining human feedback (RLHF) with small machine learning models to reduce the human cost of triplet labeling

Experience _____

Linea, Research Intern

CA, USA

June 2023 to Sept. 2023

• Worked closely with a 6-person startup team to design an initial product for Airflow pipeline reproducibility.

• Implemented a core feature that captured data lineage between Airflow tasks.

Princeton Plasma Physics Lab, Research Intern NJ, USA June 2018 to July 2018 • Generated a database from two years of experiments on the DIII-D fusion reactor using the MDSplus interface, focusing specifically on predictors for pedestal features. • Trained a fully connected neural network architecture to predict parameters that influence fusion production capabilities. Meta, Software Engineer Intern WA. USA June 2017 to Aug. 2017 • Designed an API in PHP/Hack that stores and downloads files (e.g., logs and builds) during code execution. • Combined the API with a new MySql metadata database that linked to Facebooks internal search framework. • Used to upload over 200 million log files per week, touching on most internal code development. Meta, Facebook University Intern CA, USA June 2016 to Aug. 2016 • Designed and built an independent Android app that generated playlists based on nearby concerts. • Implemented a music player in a separate service environment that linked to the Spotify API. **Publications** 2024 Quantifying Variation in Data Science Workflows with Fine-Grained Procedural Logging. Jinjin Zhao, Avigdor Gal, Sanjay Krishnan Under Submission Paper 🗹 Compression and In-Situ Query Processing for Fine-Grained Array Lineage. 2024 Jinjin Zhao, Sanjay Krishnan *ICDE* Paper **☑ Data Makes Better Data Scientists.** 2023 Jinjin Zhao, Avigdor Gal, Sanjay Krishnan AMIR: Active Multimodal Interaction Recognition from Video and Network Traffic 2023 in Connected Environments. Shinan Liu, Tarun Manla, Ted Shaowang, Jinjin Zhao, Sanjay Krishnan, Nick Feamster UbiComp/IMWUT Paper <a>Image: " Data Station: Delegated, Trustworthy, and Auditable Computation to Enable Data-2022 Sharing Consortia with a Data Escrow. Siyuan Xia, Zhiru Zhu, Chris Zhu, Jinjin Zhao, Kyle Chard, Aaron J. Elmore, Ian Foster, Michael Franklin, Sanjay Krishnan, Raul Castro Fernandez VLDB Paper 🗹 Towards Causal Query Answering for Debugging Video Analytics Systems. 2022 Ted Shaowang*, **Jinjin Zhao***, Stavos Sintos, Sanjay Krishnan Prediction of DIII-D Pedestal Structure From Externally Controllable Parameters. 2021

• Prototyped an internal large language model (LLM) tuning framework for natural

language.

Emi Zeger, Florian Laggner, Alessandro Bortolon, Cristina Rea, Orso Meneghini, Samuli Saarelma, Brian Sammuli, Sterling Smith, **Jinjin Zhao**

Experimental Based Pedestal Prediction using Machine Learning.

Jinjin Zhao, Egemen Kolemen, Xiaoyan Li, Florian Laggner

2018

APS Division of Plasma Physics Poster

Activities And Awards _

- 2018 2024 Teaching Assistant: COS 397/497 Fall 2018 (Princeton University), CMSC 16100 Autumn 2019 (University of Chicago), CMSC 21800 Autumn 2020/2023 (University of Chicago), DATA 13600 Spring 2024 (University of Chicago)
- ICDE'2024 Travel Award, NSF
- 2022 University Unrestricted Fellowship, University of Chicago
- 2020 2022 Curriculum and Social Minister, UChicago C.S. Graduate Student Ministry
- 2020 Lab Coordinator, CDAC (summer research program for high schoolers)
- OSDI'2020 Diversity Grant, USENIX Association
- 2019 Neubauer Graduate Scholarship, University of Chicago
- 2016 YHacks 1&1 Prize Winner

Skills _____

Languages: Python, SQL, C

Tools: Airflow, Amazon Web Services, Google Cloud Platform